Sherry casks and last time we saw that essentially exactly they're gonna come next week although next week's when you shouldn't drink with non-Jews. Okay so last time we saw the idea of sherry casks and the idea of a sherry cask was that it seems that really it should be assur for a number of reasons. We said according to the Shach you need to have the right amount of mevatel it and you
don't have that within the walls of the barrel. That was number one. We also saw that anything that is added for flavoring is not batel. So that was number two. Sherry cask it is added for to make things batel. Number three was if it's added for coloring it also should be a problem. And finally does it seem to rely on אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה. So after all is said and done we seem to be in a pretty difficult place that we
would allow sherry casks. So tonight we're going to see the other side of it. Why would some be meikel with these things? So we'll go step by step. Step by step. This hopefully should take us most of the time and if we have time we'll start the next sugya which is drinking in drinking together with non-Jews work related shailos things like that. Okay weiter. So if you look in source 51
it seems that there's actually an explicit Shulchan Aruch that says this. In סימן קל\"ז in hey the Shulchan Aruch says אם נתן יין בכלי אסור if you place kosher wine in a non-kosher barrel of wine that wine becomes assur because it's a min be-mino and we said min be-mino is never going to be batel. However in daled the Shulchan Aruch says כלים האסורים מחמת יין של גוים and you מותר
ליתן לתוכם מים אין שכר ואין שאר משקה. You could place water you could place beer anything else in a non-kosher barrel and that beverage is going to be mutar. So that's pretty straightforward. Sif daled in סימן קל\"ז says I can take a sherry cask which is assur that's a kli that's assur but I can put things into it. The Shach says in the right on the left side in sif katan tet-vav why? מפני שמבטלין את טעם היין because
what's happening it's nullifying and ruining the wine flavor so the flavor of wine is noten ta'am lifgam. So that's the reason that it's assur but that's the reason that it's mutar. So if you're putting a kosher beverage in a non-kosher barrel but the non-kosher barrel it's mevatel et ta'am yayin because it's noten ta'am lifgam essentially the flavor of the wine is noten ta'am lifgam then we're fine. Says the Minchas Yitzchak in source 52 that's
all fine and dandy but would not help us with sherry casks. Why? Why? Because it's put there for the ta'am. He says in the underline שהטעם שמשמש שיעור ביטול לא הוי נותן טעם לפגם אבל כיון שתכלית בנידון דידן in our situation לערב בכונה כדי שהיין יבלא לתוכו מבליעת היין that it should be the soak it up so then it wouldn't matter and it would seem to be a problem. So once again we are stuck. Seems we've run into another dead end.
Sherry casks should be assur. We are now oh for two. We're oh for two. Okay in comes Rav Moshe Feinstein. We're going to see a number of teshuvos tonight from Rav Moshe Feinstein. So first let's start in source 53 at the top of page 29 in אגרות משה יורה דעה חלק א' סימן ס\"ב. Rav Moshe is discussing where actual stam yeinam regular stam yeinam is added to whiskey. So he paskens like the Shulchan Aruch that you need one
to six and not one to sixty. So he says l'dedan big blended יש חשש שמעורב מזה חלק אחד מארבעים מותר בשתיה says you can do one to six and if you go toward in the underline he says that even the Shach who would agree why? טעמו שמשביח אסור עד ששים but in our situation חומרת התוספות עוד מצינו שיטת הרשב\"א שמשקין חריפים. Now when it comes to a charif
kind of drink wouldn't usually think of a drink as a davar charif but whiskey is a start a sharp drink and maybe that sharp drink would be mevatel anything that is inside. So now regarding the whiskey that's made in sherry casks it's unclear how much you would need or not but it does seem that Rav Moshe seems to be meikel that the whiskey that is in the barrel if you only need a little bit to mevatel that that should work.
They took the barrel, they put whiskey in there, they emptied out the whiskey, and they put whiskey in a second time and another how many years, whatever it takes. But they didn't put new wine in a sherry cask. So the second or third go-round and for sure Rav Moshe's going to say it's going to be meikel. How much more at some point that ta'am of the wine can't really be nosei ta'am into any kind of whiskey. So it seems that there would be already snif number one that they're meikel on a sherry cask. Okay.
Then you go to source... Rav Moshe's talking about you actually put wine. Correct, correct, correct, correct. Now let's go to source 54. So now we mentioned that it should be assur because it's put there for ta'am, and anything put there for taste should never be batel. So says Rav Moshe in source 54, in order for a flavor to be so significant, which we're going to talk about in a second, that it's never going to become batel, it must give off a strong flavor. So says Rav Moshe, דבר שכתוב
שהיין בזה בשביל טעמא הרי הוא כדין תבלין שאוסר אפילו בכל שהוא. מה שעשה ידידי מסורת ורמת תוספות. He says at the bottom line that anything that is not so strong then that kind of thing can be mevatel. The point, if it gives off a weak flavor, the sherry cask doesn't, you buy the whiskey, you don't be like, \"Wow, that tastes like wine.\" Then you bought the wrong product.
So if the whiskey, if the whole point of the sherry cask is to whatever, flavor it a little bit or remove some, whatever it is, but it's not to change the flavor. So that, says Rav Moshe, that we're not going to worry about, and that you could be able to be mevatel. That is source 54. You put it in so that that's the main flavor. Correct, correct, correct. The wine flavor is, the wine flavor is so weak that it could be mevatel. But many people
will hold that it's really, they put it in the cask mostly for the color. Alright, so hold on, we didn't get to that yet, we didn't get to that yet. Then you go to source 55. And to add to this, the Mishna Halacha explains it a little bit differently, a little bit differently. He says the following: הטעם דמי שמלח בחביות חדשות של עץ יש לו ריח רע ריח של עץ. The sherry flavor is actually not
absorbed into the whiskey itself. It really is preventing the negative taste of the wood. I don't know if you ever tasted wood, it doesn't taste good. So in order so that the wood doesn't give a bad flavor into the whiskey, they put wine in the cask, and that really the job of that is just so that the wood doesn't give a bad flavor to the whiskey. We're not trying to change the flavor of the whiskey. Says, Veyispog ta'am chametz, it absorbs the taste שהוא טעם של עץ בתוכו. והיין מפיק טעם וריח של
החבית החדשה. He says on the last line, ונמצא דהיין הנבלע בחבית אינו נותן טעם אינו משביחו כלל אלא פעולת היין ששולל הריח רע של החבית. The job of the wine is to limit the bad flavor of the wood. Okay, so therefore let's go back. We had four problems we said why it should be
assur. Number one, maybe you need to be mevatel. So we saw a potential Shulchan Aruch in source 51, but that might not be. So then in the Minchas Yitzchak we saw in source 52 that the sherry cask is really there, שנבלע לתוכו וריח יין, the similar idea. It's there to absorb certain things, not there to really add taste. Potentially in source 53 because whiskey is so sharp, that
maybe it actually can be mevatel. When things are sharp they can be mevatel, whatever the ratio would be. Let's assume you don't even need, the Shach would agree. Even the Shach says you need a lot more, but it's something sharp. Source 54, Rav Moshe says don't bring me the issue that it's something added for ta'am, because the sherry cask, you're right, I agree, says Rav Moshe, but this is not added for ta'am. This is either added to, either it's so that the whiskey doesn't taste like the wood, or that it's not so strong, but it's not giving a
real flavor of wine to the whiskey and therefore it's not considered something that is avida leta'ama. So so far these should be different reasons why we should be meikel. And then you go to source 56. Source 56 is the coloring. One second, didn't we say that if I add something for color, it's never batel? So in comes again the Minchas Yitzchok Dayan Weiss and he says ואדבר מעט מה שנוגע לענין חזותא when it comes for the coloring. He explains
that that is you're right. I'm not arguing, says Dayan Weiss. However, והרבה מחמירים גם בחזותא, we are machmir like this. אבל כבר הכריע הפרי חדש דבאיסור דרבנן חזותא לאו מילתא. This is not an issur d'Oraisa. This is an issur d'Rabbanan. On an issur d'Rabbanan we are not worried that something added for color is never batel. So we started with four problems we had at the end of last week why sherry cask should be a problem. Can it be actually
mevatel? Ta'am, the coloring and אין מבטל איסור לכתחילה. And Rav Moshe is saying, bitul we could probably take care of. We could take care of the coloring because it's an issur d'Rabbanan and we could take care of the ta'am. Okay. We are still left with the problem of... we did color. Color we did. Color's not a problem. Of אין מבטל איסור לכתחילה. Okay. So turn the page to source 57 to Rav
Moshe Feinstein. Once again, Rav Moshe says the following: You're right, this seems to be a problem. So each one of these steps, Rav Moshe is not arguing that אין מבטל איסור לכתחילה isn't a problem. What's אין מבטל איסור לכתחילה? So I am making meatballs and a yogurt falls in. I don't want to tell anybody because I'm in charge of dinner and I don't want to fess up that I made a mistake. So you know what I'll do? I will just add a lot more meatballs. Okay, you can't do that. That is אין מבטל איסור לכתחילה. So
if I am making whiskey in a sherry cask and I know the sherry cask has X volume, ah, I just add a lot of whiskey. We can't do that. Says Rav Moshe Feinstein in source 57. First he says, שיטת התוספות דבאיסור דרבנן שאין לו שורש מהתורה מותר לבטל איסור לכתחילה. Number one is, well, he actually adds earlier that if the company is not a Jewish
company, it's not אין מבטל איסור לכתחילה, right? They're just making whiskey. The fact that there might be more doesn't matter. So that's already number one. Then he says when it comes to an issur d'Rabbanan, like we just said, that only applies... when it came to coloring, the Dayan Weiss says that does not apply to issur d'Rabbanan. Here, Rav Moshe says the אין מבטל איסור לכתחילה applies to issurei d'Rabbanan, but only issurei d'Rabbanan that are rooted in issurei
d'Oraisa. So you're going to say, one second, didn't we learn the last three weeks that this idea is rooted in an issur d'Oraisa? What would be the issur d'Oraisa of stam yeinam? Yayin nesech. There is no yayin nesech anymore today. Why not? Because they don't use it for avoda zara. The only thing we have left today is why? Is intermarriage. That's an issur d'Rabbanan. That's not based on anything in the Torah. So says Rav Moshe Feinstein, a great chiddush. He says, if you have a d'Rabbanan
that is אין לו שורש מהתורה מותר לבטל איסור לכתחילה ולא רק להוסיף אלא הרי מתחילה. Not only that, I could mix it together completely. We know that the idea of yayin nesech the Rama says doesn't apply anymore. There is no libations anymore. They don't do that. So then he writes in the bottom, he says however, and we'll come back to this in a second but let's just finish this top
paragraph: אם כן מסתבר דסתם יינם בזמן הזה דמותרים בהנאה כדרכינו נחשב אין לו שורש מהתורה כיון שהוא רק מצד איסור חתנות. The only reason we have this today is because of chasnus. Chasnus is only an issur d'Rabbanan. It is not modeled after any issur d'Oraisa. And therefore says Rav Moshe, you can mevatel issur l'chatchila. First of all, this tremendous chiddush of Rav Moshe Feinstein. We have learned in this chabura long enough to see
the brilliance of Rav Moshe Feinstein, how he is able to learn a sugya and with such clarity understand how things are. That's why Rav Moshe was a tremendous ba'al m'chadesh. I mean, he's not the only one who says this, but it's a tremendous chiddush. Okay now. So we first thought we should not allow sherry casks. That's if you came last week. Okay? If you came back this week, we saw that potentially we should be okay. Number one, the whole bitul should be okay because the, you know, there is
if you need one to sixty we should be okay, probably only absorbs k'dei klipa. And even the Shach Rav Moshe says would be okay because it's so charif, it's so sharp that it's mevatel whatever the bit in the barrel is. self, even the Shach would agree, so that we've taken care of, we're good. We said, if it absorbs more than a k'dei klipa you probably need one to sixty then. There you go, yeah, correct, correct. That was issue number 1, we seem to be okay with that. What about if something is added for flavor? So Rav Moshe says it's a very weak flavor, it's not doing much.
And the Mishne Halachot says it's not even given for flavor, it's just given to fend off the negative wood, wood taste. So all right, we should be okay. What about coloring? You're right, coloring should never be mevattel, but that's only on issur d'oraysa. Issur d'rabbanan we should be okay with. And what about אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה? We should also be okay with, because that's only on an issur d'rabbanan that's rooted in an issur d'oraysa, which this is not. Okay. Then says Rav Moshe back in source 57. However, now
this is probably one of the best examples to understand what does it mean when a posek says בעל נפש יחמיר על עצמו? Meaning, last week we learned through pretty clear sources that it should be assur. Granted, we have learned through today a number of sources that it appears if you add them all together that it should be muttar. Great. So says Rav Moshe, ולדינא בעל נפש יש לו להחמיר, that a baal nefesh
should be stringent. Why? על עצמו מצד כמה חששות because I needed to rely on this opinion of the Mishne Halachot, I needed to rely on this opinion of, I have to rely on a lot of things in order to make this work. Again, it's okay, Rav Moshe is not against it, but a baal nefesh should be machmir. And he explains, חדא דהרבה פוסקים סברי דסתם יינם גם בזמן הזה אסור בהנאה. Not everybody says what we just said, and it could be that even today stam
yeinam is a problem. Fine. Number 2, ואף דהמתירין יש סברי דוקא במקום הפסד. Maybe we're only allowed to do this if it's makom hefsed. It could be you own the sherry casks, you own the company, whatever it is. ואם כן למה שביארתי שיש לאדם הנאה ממים שנותן לשם מד יין דתבשיל לא נחשב מתירים שיהיו יותר בשביל היין לא גרע דמקיים מהנאה בעלמא שרי. Rav Moshe says in the end of the day, you're right, you know, number 1, many hold stam yeinam is still a problem.
Number 2, even if we have these things that the taam is not so, it's still added for something. It's added for something. We might disagree what taam flavor impact goes in from the sherry cask to the wine. At the end of the day, it's something. To what degree it is, that's a big question. Okay? Then Rav Moshe says according to the Shach, really the first what's called first-fill casks would be a bigger problem. The first time they use that sherry cask, the flavor of the wine
is going to be stronger. So in the end of the day, we should be machmir, and that's why in the end, because of Rav Moshe and then because of Rav Belsky also, the OU does not, we'll talk about CRC a different time, but at least for the SCP purposes, they quoted the OU and the OU doesn't give a hechsher to it, they don't give a hechsher on sherry casks, and they don't give a hechsher on events that have it, because there's a lot of kulos that go into it. It's okay, and Rav Moshe would be
okay drinking it if one would have to, but at the same time, one should try and be machmir. Okay. The way, if you look though in two more sources, in 58 and 59, we will see that there are those that are meikil. If you look in source 58 of the Mishne Halachot, it's the Ungvarer Rav, ואשר כן לפני עניות דעתי שאינו רוצה לשתות whisky עד שיתברר לו האמת that if you are, you know, he has a very, very long teshuvah and he says, at the end of the day, if you don't want to drink the whisky, עד
שיתברר לו האמת כשר נעשה בחבית של יין נסך ורוצה להתרחק מן הכיעור ומן הדומה תבא עליו ברכה. You're right, you, good. אבל מצד הלכה ליתא says the Mishne Halachot, you could do that if you want, but I think it's okay. Why? ומי ששתה ודאי אינו צריך תשובה על מה ששתה. And if you drank sherry cask liquor then you came to Semichas Chaver, you shouldn't be going home and clapping al chet. Generally
if you keep doing issurim and then clapping al chet, that's another problem. But says the Ungvarer Rav, it's fine. Could you be machmir if you wanted to? Yes. There are, meaning Rav Moshe says you could allow it but it's better not to. Right? There's different language the Rav Moshe, I'm talking about sometimes baal nefesh, but he's pretty clear that it's not ideal. Then there's Mishne Halachot that says there is what to be machmir on, but at the same time I'm totally okay with it and you didn't do anything wrong. And then you get in source 59, you get to Rav Asher Weiss shlita. So
says Rav Asher Weiss. So Rav Asher Weiss not only does he allow it, he allows even the first-fill cask. Okay, so we've now gone to the other, the other side. So poshute... פשוט דהכרח לומר באחת משתי דרכים להגיע אחת משתי מסקנות. He says, I'm going to have two reasons why it's going to be okay. Aleph, be'emes ein טעם יין משביח כלל את הויסקי. Number one, it is not doing anything. That ta'am of the Sherry cask is doing nothing to
the whiskey itself. וכבר הבאתי לעיל שגם בין המומחים ונחזי הטעם מחולק אם שינוי טעם יין משביח את הויסקי לרובא דעלמא אין טעם יין מורגש כלל. Most of the time you don't taste the Sherry cask at all. You don't taste the wine at all. Okay? You don't taste the wine at all. Second. Af im ha-whiskey ochen mishtabeach and even if, fine, it does do something, אין זה משום טעם יין ופליטתו אלא
משום ריאקציה כימית של עץ האלון והשרי. It's really the wood that is doing something but not the wine. Meaning they don't take whiskey, put it in a ziplock bag and dump it into a bottle of a barrel of wine. There is something about the wood. So if there is a flavor that is being given off, it's really the wood that has the, you know, a little bit of this relationship with the, with the wine, but not really anything at all. And
therefore says Rav Asher Weiss, it'll be mutter completely, even first-fill casks. So that in a nutshell is the 157-page article from the CRC on this topic. There's a lot of reason to say yes, there's a lot of reason to say no. You know, a majority of poskim are going to say it is better to refrain if one doesn't need to have Sherry cask. That doesn't mean if you went to a, I don't know, you went to a business meeting and the guy offered you Sherry cask whiskey, and
saying it would be a problem, we're going to see in a second, I would probably be meikel. And then you have the Minchas Halacha who says it's fine, and you have Rav Asher Weiss who says it's for sure fine. Okay. Fine. And that would be the same thing for any...? Yeah, yeah, same thing, yeah, same thing, same thing. Okay. Before we get into the next topic, which is drinking wine with non-Jews, there is a small thing here about brandy. Does anybody drink brandy? Special occasion. On occasion. Learning
a lot about you tonight, Andy. Okay. Brandy is. Special occasion. Special occasion. Okay. Brandy is very expensive. The only time I ever drank brandy, I think, was I was in, I was in Montreal for Torah Tours. And we got to this very wealthy, fancy person's house and he offered us a nightcap. Yeah, exactly. That's what I said. Yeah. And I think
they drink brandy in the movie Titanic at some point. That's, that's it. That's my only association. Here we go. So, anybody know how brandy is made? Grapes. Grapes. Great. Okay. Okay. Okay. So back in the times of Chazal there was something called a gas, which is a winepress. So today obviously we don't use a winepress. They have a whole thing here which you can read about about what, what used to be, but I'm just going to read this to you because just to put us all on the same page. When grapes arrive at the winery, the stems are removed. The grapes are crushed.
In order to make red wine, red grapes are crushed, stored with their skins and seeds for at least five days. During this time the wine develops its red color. Fermentation begins. After this initial stage, liquid is separated from the skins and seeds and aged in barrels for several months. In contrast, producing white wine from white or green grapes, the grape seeds are removed immediately and the clear juice is set aside to begin the fermentation process. Great. Says the Gemara. Says the Gemara in source 60, the Gemara in Avodah Zarah. אמר רב הונא יין.
So the Gemara says that wine, keivan she-his'chil le-himashech, once it begins to, you know, be separated, oseh yayin nesech. That has the status of wine. That means that if there is, if there are some grapes and the grapes start to have a little bit of liquid and then a non-Jew touches that liquid, that liquid is yayin nesech. That liquid is going to be yayin nesech. If you look in the Shulchan Aruch, okay, if you go open the Shulchan Aruch and you go to
קכג יז. Exactly like this Gemara says, מאימתי נקרא יין לאסור במגע עובד כוכבים? When exactly does a wine become assur that if a goy would touch it, it would become, you know, yayin nesech? דהיינו משימשך על הגת בעצמו. Really exactly what we just said. As it begins to separate even within the winepress,
the winepress itself is considered... Why? Yud zayin, קכג יז. ואם פינה מהחרצנים והזגים והיין לבדו נמשך מצד העליון לצד התחתון and again the same thing, once everything begins to separate to one side, it is considered wine. Okay, we're not going to do the whole Yud zayin, go to Yud chet. So the Shulchan Aruch says in seif yud chet the following.
Right, so essentially, again, we'd have to be more up to date with the wine production stages of how wine is made, but during initial stages of wine production today, a goy touching it would not seem to be an issue. In seif yud chet the Shulchan Aruch paskens that all these things, that they're all sort of mixed together, says אם מילא מהגת כוס יין. If you filled up a cup, וכיון לשלוסו מהחרצנים והזגים, and you took all of the juices, the
grape skins, the seeds all mixed together in one big barrel, and you removed a clear cup of that juice, and you're going to take it and separate it from the seeds and the skin and all that stuff, then that's considered hamshacha. That is nikra hamshacha, that's called being drawn out, and if a goy were to touch that cup and that wine it would be a problem. The Shulchan Aruch continues, but if אם לקח החרצנים או יין, but if you really like took it out to like, you know, look at it, to investigate, it would not be considered, you
know, yayin nesech. Okay. See, go to source 61 in the book hood. The ספר בין ישראל לעמים paskens the following, based on the Beis Yosef, that אם הוציא הישראל כוס יין מהגת, if a took out a cup, לבדוק את טיבו שלו היין, if you wanted to check what's the story with this, אם טוב או כמה קושי סוכר יש בו, have to add anything, lo nechshav hamshacha.
That's not considered hamshacha. Okay. In the end though he writes that if I'm just taking it out to test, you know, the levels of sugar, whatever I need to add, it's not going to be a problem. If a goy, what? The wine in the cup would be assur. Everything else would be assur. Everything else would be assur, but then he writes in the next paragraph in yud daled lema'aseh today, you know, when grapes are like brought in, you know, he writes this whole thing, but, you know, they're brought in, they go in and they crush a few, there it's not really going to be
such a, you know, such a problem. Okay. If anybody ever watched I Love Lucy, so if you go to if you go to chaf aleph, you'll see that this is a similar idea. If you go to chaf aleph, just to finish this quickly, the Shulchan Aruch paskens that a non-Jew stomps on grapes, אין דורכין עם העובד כוכבים בגת, that actually forbids the grapes, because we're concerned he might touch it with his hands. Shema yiga beyado.
So even though it might not be a problem right away, we asser it, because he might touch it with his hands. The Rama clarifies this that whatever in the end of the day, I don't know how much this really does apply to so many people here in terms of how many wines you are going to be crushing at home. Okay. You can just look one more in source 62 and then we'll move on. In source 62, so basically in order for brandy to be kosher, you need a hechsher.
That's the bottom line, because of how it's made. There you go. You need a hechsher. So if you weren't sure, now you know. Sar haYashiv says two reasons why it needs מותר לשתות קוניאק וברנדי אדם החשוב בכל השנה בשעת הגזירה. He says on the third line, ונגע הגוי מתרי טעמי אחדא דין מבושל. So he says, venaga hagoy touches them, like these these once they're produced, these kind of grapes, it would be okay, they're mevushal, that's number one, and second of all, they've changed so much
that it really wouldn't be a problem if they touched the brandy afterwards, it's not if you have brandy at your house and a goy touches it, it's not yayin nesech anymore. It's mevushal in the bottles too. Right. Okay, that's what he says. It's all in the bottles. Right. Isn't everything distilled mevushal? That's what his point is. Correct. Correct. Okay, fine. Good. That was quick. Let's go to the next very interesting topic. Because basically the process in order to make the wine evaporate and re-condense.
Right. Okay. Source 63. Okay. So we are going to learn about drinking with non-Jews. Says the Gemara, itmar, מפני מה אסרו שכר של עובדי כוכבים. Why is non-Jewish beer assur? רמי בר חמא אמר רב יצחק משום חתנות. Because of... Was what's chasnus? Intermarriage, right? Ah, it's going to lead to intermarriage,
and second the Gemara says רב נחמן אמר משום גילוי because what happened, the non-Jews often keep their beer exposed overnight, the issue of mashkin megulim can leave things overnight. Okay. The Gemara then adds רב פפא מפיקין ליה לאבבא דחנותא that Rav Pappa, they were both sort of wait till it was brought outside of the store ve-shasi and רב אחאי אייתי ליה לביתיה ושתי and Rav Achai would
also wait until it was brought outside of his home, that's where he would drink it, meaning where was he not drinking it? Inside. In the non-Jewish place. Ve-tarvaihu mishum chasnus. Ve-tarvaihu mishum chasnus. Okay. Very simple Gemara. Now look at source sixty-four. So the question is as follows: if you're telling me that it's asur, why does it all of a sudden automatically become better when now you brought it to my house or you brought it outside the bar? So I can't go into
the bar and drink the wine, but you're telling me that if I brought it outside the bar, according to Rav Acha or according to Rav Pappa or Rav Achai I brought it to my house, then all of a sudden everything becomes okay. So a number of answers to this question, but look in the Ramban. So the Ramban explains the following, why are we going to be more lenient? And he says ונימוקי חכמי הצרפתים מצאתי בשכר ראשונים לא אסרו מעולם. You're right, the what the Gemara is telling you
is a later addition. This wasn't always the case, beer wasn't always asur. אבל אחרונים נהגו בו חשש חתנות, later they saw things were getting a little bit dicey. So what did they do? They made a gezeira: don't drink in the bar. ונראה שמפני זה מקילין שלא נאסר בביתן. So therefore we are going to be much more lenient. We're going to be much more lenient, meaning it's not really, it's asur, but it's only asur
in the exact thing we said: we said you can't drink it in the place, but if you bring it outside it's going to be okay. So what are some of those leniencies? So look at Tosafos in source sixty-five, three more leniencies he explains. Number one, מיהו מאכסניא דעובדי כוכבים פעמים שיכול להיות שמותר לשלוח beer שכר מעובדי כוכבים והוי כמו ביתו של ישראל, because
like my inn is my home, so I can order beer to my house. All right, good. Two, ועם עובדי כוכבים אכסנאי שלו. You know, this is back, we're not telling you that the, you know, the hotel receptionist of the, you know, the Marriott is having a beer with you. Hava back in the old days when there was an inn, so the innkeeper said, \"Hey, let's have a drink together.\" So says Tosafos, if he offers you a drink noten lo mishelo, he says, \"Hey, have
some of my beer,\" mishum eyva. What does that mean? Because of animosity. We don't say, \"Oh, the guy offered you pork, that's mishum eyva.\" Nice, he's going to be insulted if you don't eat the pork. We don't say that. You can't throw eyva out there for like, \"Listen, if I don't drive on Shabbos it's going to be eyva,\" but you can say eyva, you can say animosity, when it's a low-level issur de-rabbanan. So says Tosafos, you're worried about it, it's only asur because of chasnus, so
I'm going to have this drink with him. And finally, he says a very important one לקבוע שתייה בחנות וברגילות לשתות בבית עובדי כוכבים, this only when it's like an established place, aval be-akray, but like randomly a drinking, like at a one-time thing, that's going to be okay. Okay, good. So we seem to be pretty lenient about it. What's included? What's included in this issur? Is everything included in this issur?
Are all alcoholic drinks included in this issur? So says the Tur in source sixty-six, all beer is included. Okay כל שכר אחד שכר תמרים של שעורים וכי משקה עשוי מדבש. Whatever you want, beer, date beer, wheat beer, no, honey beer, asurin mishum chasnus, meaning it's all, all of that beer is included in this prohibition, in the prohibition of drinking it at a... Shechar beer refers to beer?
Yep, yeah, yeah. Then in the Beis Yosef though, in source sixty-seven, he says hold on a second כפסק תוספות וכל דין שכר בין של תמרים בין של תבואה. Right, according to Tosafos, it seems like only alcoholic drinks are a problem דשכר שלנו אין בו משום חתנות ונראה דטעמו מפני שסובר דכיון דלא אשכחן דאסר השכר אלא רב פפא. meaning only alcoholic beer, alcoholic drink should be אין לאסור רק כמין שיכרא שלהם.
We can only model what they did. What they did was alcoholic drinks, so we should asur alcoholic drinks. And therefore that should only be the thing that that's in the prohibition. The, you know, he's saying only shel temarim. Shel temarim, yeah yeah. So not shel se'orim or so like only, I don't know, drink shel temarim. Ah, so saying not, he's saying beer is shel temarim, so we can only... Well, what their temarim was is was more... Correct.
Right. אבל לא של שעורים או של מינים אחרים. Yeah. Fine. So now let's look at how we pasken. So look at the Shulchan Aruch in the next, in the next source, in source 68. Okay. So let's go slow. Not too slow, because getting late. כל שיכרא של עובד כוכבים. So like Tosafot: כל שכר של עובדי כוכבים אחד שכר של תמרים של תאנים של שעורים של תבואה של דבש יאסר משום חתנות. Exactly like we just said:
dates, figs, barley, honey drinks, they're all forbidden because they lead, may lead to intermarriage. ואינו אסור אלא מקום מכירתו, they're only asur really in the place where you drink them. אבל אם הביא השכר לביתו ושותהו שם מותר שעיקר הגזרה שמא יסעד אצלו. The whole point of the issur is what? That I'm going to like have this farbreng together with you. I'm not going to farbreng with you if you're at my house. ולא אסרו אלא כשקובע עצמו לשתות כדרך שהיו קובעים
בשתיה. But if I go into my, you know, partner's house, my the my CEO is offering drinks and I never go there and it's a once-in-a-thing, that's not a- it's not a established pattern thing that I do. Therefore, he says it would be okay. Okay? So it would have to be those drinks in a consistent, permanent manner, that seems to be when it's asur.
The Shach, like we just said in se'if katan bet on the left side, the Shach says: ואף אם עובד כוכבים מכניסה לתוך ביתו ונותן לו לשתות משום איבה. Same thing, even if he gives it to you, you should drink it because of eivah. We do not want this causing animosity. We have the non-Jews already hate us enough. We don't have, right? It was a big win today when the guys that went on the Empire State Building were not, were not pro-Palestinian. It was like a win, right? Like there wasn't the flag that they put out. It was great. It was a big win
for us today. So okay, fine. Now, in source 69, so says the Kaf Hachayim, quoting the Pri Chadash, he says: peirush tartei ba'inan. He says: two things are necessary in order for you to have a drink, to drink a beer in a non-Jewish location. I imagine, I assume most people do like beer. I don't like beer. I used to go to ballgames with my father, my father would get a beer, there's nothing better he wanted than was to sit outside in
like Baltimore heat on a Sunday afternoon at Camden Yards, like, take me to a 7:00 game, great. 1:00 PM with a, you know, that was his, you know, that's what he always thought was the best. So can you drink, which is going to be a she'eilah if you could drink a beer at a ballgame. I hope we're- hoping it's going to be okay. I mean you're paying 14 dollars, but... So number one, he says: דרך עראי שלא בקביעות. Okay? It has to be done in a non-permanent manner. Not the times
that I do it, but even when I'm doing it, it has to be like I'm not really here, you know, like the guy who sits with his arm- who leans against the wall at a Terrace on the Park for the chuppah when there's 50 seats available, because he- he might have to go, you know? I'm drinking it but I might have to leave. So that's number one. ועראי דהיינו שלא רגיל בכך. Okay? So I have to- it must not be done consistently. Veragilut, he says
at the bottom, what does it mean consistently? It means shalosh pe'amim. Okay, it means three times. So three times. So now before you, we go on, go back to the Rema in source 68. Go back to the Rema in source 68. The Rema in source 68: ויש מתירים בשיכרא של דבש ותבואה וכן נוהגים להקל במדינות אלו. So says the- no, we look,
read that one more time, because if you look in the non-underlined, but the parentheses, he's quoting the Mordechai here. Mordechai in the name of the Ravyah and the Beit Yosef. And he says harbei mei'acharonim that only date beer is what's prohibited because that was the beverage commonly consumed, but all other forms of beer would be permitted. And the Rema says vechein noheig. It's a big one for us, we got... at a Rama's who's meikel. וכן נוהגין להקל במדינות אלו that many Jews drink beer with non-Jews in non-Jewish establishments and it seems to
be that that's the... that's the... that's where... that's how we're meikel. That's how we're meikel. If you... there's no Gra here, but whatever, we can see a Gra different time. Anyway, okay. So it seems that the scene in Tevarya, where Tevarya is drinking with the Rabbanan, it's okay. Right. There you go. What a... what a raya! They didn't include that one in the notes.
Okay. So again, to summarize, if you go... if you look in the Shulchan Aruch one more time, drinking any type of beer or non-alcoholic drink in the home of a non-Jew or establishment of a non-Jew is a problem. But we are lenient number one if it's drunk in a non-permanent manner or non-consistent basis. If you're ordering it to your hotel room, it's fine because that's considered your home. If it's eivah, we're also going to be okay. And potentially the Rama says only a certain kind of beer is going to be assur but everything else is
going to be allowed. Okay. Fine. We'll hold it here. So next time we're going to pick up with a bunch of examples and then we should wrap up hopefully Kuf Chaf Gimmel next week. Very exciting. Okay, shkoach.